

# Nuno Miguel MARTINS PACHECO

Location: Munich, Germany E-mail: nuno.pacheco@outlook.de LinkedIn: martinspacheco

## **PROFILE**

I am a creative and determined project lead with over 6 years of experience in product development and innovation management. Specializing in design thinking and agile methods, I have proven that I can successfully realize complex projects. My background in mechanical engineering and my PhD in product development at TUM have sharpened my technical and analytical skills. During my time at university, I have successfully collaborated with industrial partners such as BMW and MAN as well as academic partners such as Imperial College London. My passion is to have a positive impact on the sustainable development through innovative projects.

# WORK EXPERIENCE

07/2019 - Current

#### RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

- Since July 2019 project lead for THINK. MAKE. START, an innovation format at BMW and TUM, among others, in which new product ideas are developed and implemented, as well as MCube STEAM, a publicly funded research project for the development of new public transport concepts

#### Overview of projects:

10/2021 - Current

Co-Project Lead

## MCube STEAM in collaboration with BMW, MAN, SWM and Stanglmeier

- Ensuring the success of the publicly funded research project with a volume of ~ EUR 1.5 million
- Implementation and execution of progress reports, status meetings and workshops
- Concept development lead for an integrated public transport bus system and realization VR demonstrator (IAA Mobility 2023)

07/2019 - Current

Co-Project Lead & Coach

## THINK. MAKE. START. in collaboration with BMW

- Organization of sprints for the development of customer-centric, innovative products
- Coaching of cross-functional teams (~ 50 employees per sprint) in prototyping, storytelling and design thinking

07/2019 - 03/2024

**Project Lead** 

#### THINK. MAKE. START. in collaboration with UnternehmerTUM, Makerspace and Zeidler Forschungsstiftung

- Organization of sprints as part of a university seminar as project manager
- Coaching of cross-functional teams (~ 60 students per sprint) in prototyping, storytelling, design thinking and product strategy

02/2022 - Current

## CO-PROJECT LEAD WORKSHOP DEVELOPMENT (Freelancer)

Mintech Engineering GmbH, Garching, Germany

- Development and implementation of technology-focused workshops for design thinking and prototyping in the B2B environment (e.g. BMW, Siemens)
- Coaching of cross-functional teams (~ 30 employees per sprint) in brainstorming, prototyping, storytelling and design thinking

## **EDUCATION**

09/2019 - Current

## PhD. DOCTOR'S DEGREE, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

- Specialisation: Product development of mechatronics products, design sprints
- PhD Thesis: A Hackathon Approach for Design Education to Enable Quantitative Analysis of Effort Spent, Product Concept Quality, and Learning Effect in Technical Higher Education (Thesis submitted 05/2024)

## **EDUCATION**

12/2022 & 05/2023

# VISITING RESEARCHER, DESIGN ENGINEERING

Imperial College London, London, England

10/2016 - 05/2019

## M.Sc. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING AND MANAGEMENT

Technical University of Munich (TUM), Munich, Germany

- Specialisation: Product development, production and innovation
- Master Thesis: Prototyping Recommendation Framework; A Collection of Prototyping Methods for Early-Stage Product Development

02/2018 - 06/2018

## SEMESTER ABROAD, MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

Instituto Superior Técnico (IST), Lisbon, Portugal

10/2011 - 10/2011

## **B.Sc. MECHANICAL ENGINEERING AND ECONOMICS**

Technical University of Graz (TUG), Graz, Austria

- Specialisation: Engineering sciences with a foundation in natural sciences and business economics
- Bachelor Thesis: Business Creation, Factors Influencing this Decision, and Importance of Entrepreneurial Universities

02/2002 - 06/2011

## **GENERAL HIGHER EDUCATION QUALIFICATION**

Taunusgymnasium Königstein, Königstein im Taunus, Germany

# KNOWLEDGE AND SKILLS

- IT Skills
- MS Office (very good)
- Miro (very good)
- Adobe Creative Cloud (good)
- Notion (good)
- Trello (good)
- Confluence (very good)
- Jira (basic)
- Python (basic)
- R (good)
- Figma/Adobe XD (basic)

## Language Skills

- German (native)
- English (business fluent)
- Portuguese (native)
- Spanish (basic)
- Italian (basic)

# OTHER

# Mitgliedschaften

- Design Society (since 2019)
- Verein Deutscher Ingenieure (since 2023)
- Deutscher Alpenverein (since 2024)

## Interessen

- Road biking
- Hiking
- Analog Photography
- Cooking